This is the transmission of Dahuangting.
这就是大黄庭传功
Sure enough, Wudang has pledged allegiance to North Liang.
武当果然已经归顺北椋
Your Grace.
公主
This is our chance now.
眼下正是时机
How is that?
此话怎讲
If we stop them now,
此时打断他们二人
the internal force will render Xu Fengnian's meridians disorderly,
让内气冲乱徐凤年的经脉
and he will be ruined.
他整个人就废了
Just a moment, Your Grace.
公主请稍等
But if you do this,
可你这么做
Xu Xiao will hate you.
徐骁岂不恨死你
How can we depend on Xu Xiao?
徐骁岂能依靠
Good.
好
If you make it,
你若成事
the court will issue a decree
朝廷必将传旨
and make you the master of Wudang.
封你为武当掌门
Thanks.
多谢
Let's do it together.
一起出手
Who is that?
这又是谁
Brother Wang.
小王师兄
How did you come out of the Purple Bamboo Forest?
怎么从紫竹林里出来了
Don't go any farther.
别再上前了
If we don't stop them,
再这么下去
Master Chonglou will lose all his force.
掌门师兄一身功力就全废了
It's his own decision.
这是师兄自己的决定
There isn't much time left.
怕是要来不及了
It's done.
完了
It's too late.
来不及了
Your Grace.
殿下
It's destined that it can't be done.
事不可为啊
Let's go.
还是走吧
You ruined Wudang!
你们这是害了武当
Little Taoist.
小道士
Do you want to come down with us?
要不要跟我们一起下山
Your Grace.
公主
I won't go with you.
我就不下山了
Master Chonglou lost all his force.
掌门师兄功力全失
Wudang will elect a new master.
武当定会重选掌门
I'd like to try it.
我想试试
If I could be the master,
若能成为掌门
maybe I could turn the tide.
或能力挽狂澜
Very good.
很好
Rest assured.
你放心
The court will fully support you to take over Wudang.
朝廷必定全力支持你接任武当
Thank you, Your Grace.
多谢公主
Xu Fengnian will wake up soon.
那徐凤年快醒了
Please leave as soon as possible.
还请公主速速离开
You acted well.
小王师兄演得不错
There was more action than talk.
少说话多动手
It was not that difficult.
也不算难
Let's check Master Chonglou.
去看看掌门师兄吧
Master Chonglou.
师兄
Did it go well?
没出差错
The Princess should have believed it.
公主应该是相信了
Use the force of North Liang as a deterrent to Mount Longhu,
借北椋之威震慑龙虎山
then with the support of the capital,
再让京城为你助力
it will be a sure thing
这样一来你接手武当
for you to take over Wudang.
就万无一失了
Master Chonglou.
师兄
Don't be sullen.
别苦着脸
Use my Dahuangting
用我这身大黄庭
to change for the future for Wudang.
为武当换个未来
It's worth it.
这是赚了
Do you know why
你手上的这把神荼
the Shentu Sword
交到你的手里
was given to you?
你当知道为了什么
To guard Wudang.
守山
The world is turbulent.
风雨飘摇
Before you become the best in the world,
师弟成就天下第一之前
we must count on you
武当就靠
to guard Wudang
你的这把桃木剑
with this mahogany sword.
来守成了
I'll live and die
我在
with Wudang.
武当便在
You go up first.
你们都先上去
Gather your fellow apprentices.
召唤诸位师兄弟
I have something to say.
过会儿我有话说
What about you, Master Chonglou?
那你呢
I'll wait for him to wake up.
我等他醒来
Go ahead.
去吧
Your Grace.
殿下
We've seen no pursuers.
未见有人追来
Let's go back to the capital now.
即刻回京城
Yes, Your Grace.
是 殿下
Should we send a message
那徐凤年
to the capital right now
得到内力之事
that Xu Fengnian got the internal force?
要不要即刻传信京城
Xu Fengnian is nothing but a fool.
徐凤年不过是个蠢材
So what that he acquired martial arts?
有武功又怎样
In terms of the momentum of history,
在天下大势面前
one person's capability
个人武勇
is not worth mentioning.
不值一提
You are quite right, Your Grace.
殿下所言极是
Send the message about Wudang back now.
倒是先把武当的消息传回去
One thing is for sure
可以确认
that Wudang has defected to North Liang.
武当已经归顺北椋
Ask Mount Longhu not to be too aggressive.
叫龙虎山别太强势了
We can't provoke Xu Xiao
不能为了一个小小的门派
just for a little sect.
去挑衅徐骁
Yes, Your Grace.
是 殿下
I will send a message to the capital immediately.
我这就放出飞鸽传书京城
And also,
还有
Hong Xixiang's heart is with the capital.
洪洗象心向京城
We should support him
尽量支持他
to take over Wudang.
接掌武当
Why are my clothes not wet?
衣服怎么没湿啊
The water has been evaporated.
已经蒸干了
You lit a fire?
点火了
The genuine spirit works better than fire.
真气比火好用
You've passed Dahuangting to me?
已经把大黄庭给我了
Yes.
给了
I don't feel any difference.
没感觉有什么不同啊
Looks like you are compatible with my genuine spirit.
看来世子还挺契合这真气
As for how much of the genuine spirit you can keep,
真气能留下几成
it depends on your fate.
就看你自己的造化了
Thank you.
多谢
You want to go up to the mountain?
要上山顶
Let me help you.
我扶你
Thank you.
有劳世子了
In order to protect Wudang,
为了护住武当
I threw
我把自个儿这条命
my life away.
都扔出去了
Wudang
武当
is not a big sect, but it's not small, either.
好歹也算个不大不小的门派
It's even hard for us to survive in this world.
要在这世上求活都如此不易
How hard the lives would be
那些真正的平民百姓
for the common people?
又该有多么艰难呢
If one day
若日后有朝一日
please
请世子一定
consider them.
为他们想想
I will.
一定
Why are you waiting here?
怎么等在这儿了
To help you go up the mountain.
扶你上山
Good.
也好
Then I won't trouble Your Highness.
那就不用辛苦世子了
Yeah.
是啊
It's almost the end of the year.
眼下年关将近
You should go back to North Liang.
世子也该回北椋了
You knew about the passing of Dahuangting?
传功的事你早就知道
Please
还请世子
don't waste it.
不要浪费了大黄庭
I'll wait for the news that you set foot in Wudi City.
我等你踏上武帝城头的消息
Your Grace.
公主殿下
I'll get some hot water
我得去备些热开水
to make tea for you.
好给殿下沏茶呀
Why are you following me?
跟着我干什么
You should guard Her Grace now!
这时候应该去守护公主殿下
Yes.
是
Fill it with hot water.
去灌壶热开水
How is it going?
怎么样了
Things have changed.
情况有变
What happened?
怎么回事
That person was taken away by the people of Mount Longhu.
人被龙虎山接走了
It should be written by Jian Jiuhuang.
应该是剑九黄的手笔
And His Highness...
还有世子
What's wrong with His Highness?
世子怎么了
Wang Chonglou
王重楼
passed Dahuangting to him.
将一身大黄庭传给世子了
Princess Suizhu has believed
隋珠公主已经认定
that Wudang has pledged allegiance to North Liang.
武当归属北椋
To protect themselves?
自保
Aside from this accident,
除了这点意外
everything else went on just as you expected.
其余都如王爷所想
Princess Suizhu
隋珠公主
saw with her own eyes that His Highness is obstreperous and stupid.
亲眼见到世子顽劣不堪
From now on,
从今往后
the capital won't be wary of His Highness.
京城应该会对世子放心了
By the way.
对了
Father wants me to ask you
义父让我问你
if you want to find a chance
要不要找个机会
to go back to North Liang.
回北椋啊
My stay in the capital
我留在京城
will help His Lordship more.
对王爷更有用处
Thank you.
你辛苦了
I'll leave.
走了
Your Grace.
公主殿下
We are ready to go.
可以出发了
Did you pay for it?
给钱了吗
Yes.
给过了
Five pennies.
五文钱
It's not easy for these people.
这些小民也是辛苦
Send five more pennies to the owner.
给店家再送五文
Sir.
客官
Is there anything else I can do for you?
您还有什么吩咐吗
Your tip.
赏你的
Thank you very much.
那可多谢您了
Your Grace.
殿下
The money has been given to him.
钱给到了
Let's go.
出发吧
Yes.
是
Sun Diaosi is right.
孙貂寺说的没错
Princess Suizhu
隋珠公主
is suspicious deep down
刁蛮的外表下
in spite of her unruly behavior.
藏着颗多疑的心
Don't leave anything!
什么都别剩
Burn everything you see!
能烧都烧了
Let's go to Wudang
去武当
and take His Highness home!
接世子回家
Wang Chonglou is daring indeed.
王重楼有气魄
I wasn't expecting this, either.
我也没料到会是这样
Two months is up.
两个月时间早就到了
I should probably leave.
我也该走了
You won't go back to North Liang with me?
您不跟我回北椋了
Everyone has his path.
每个人都有自己的路要走
We have to say goodbye
途中遇上的
to those we meet on the way.
总会道别
This is the world of martial arts.
这就是江湖
Thank you for your teachings.
多谢前辈授业之恩
Keep practicing martial arts.
好好练刀
Maybe we will meet again.
有缘再见
I'm leaving.
走了
Here you are.
都来了
- Master.
掌门
Good.
好
From today on,
从今日起
Wudang has
武当算是
survived the calamity of extermination.
逃过了灭门之祸
I only have one thing to tell you.
我只有一句话告诉诸位
After my death,
我死之后
Hong Xixiang
洪洗象
will take over Wudang and become the master.
接任武当掌门
Master Chonglou.
师兄
I think I can't erase it.
好像擦不掉啊
This is Dahuangting.
这就是大黄庭
Jiang Ni.
姜泥
Do you think I shouldn't have come to Wudang?
你说我是不是不应该来武当啊
Don't complain when it's in your interest.
别得了便宜卖乖
Pass it to me if you don't want it.
你如果不要可以给我
I'll die if I pass it to you.
传功会死人的
That would be the best.
死了最好
Besides, I don't know how to pass it.
再说我也不会传
Your Highness!
世子
Your Highness, have you missed me?
你想我了没有啊
I miss you so much!
禄球儿想死你啦
Jiang Ni.
姜泥
It's time to go home.
咱们该回家了
Your Highness!
世子
Fatty Lushan is coming!
禄球儿来了
You can stay here for a few more days if you want.
喜欢可以多住几天
That won't be necessary.
没必要
Master Wang said
掌门师兄说他
it will take him too long to go down the mountain,
现在上下山太慢
so he won't come to bid farewell.
所以就不送世子了
Tell him for me
你帮我转告他
I won't forget
我欠武当的
what I owe Wudang.
永远不会忘
Um.
嗯
This is Wudang's book on practicing genuine spirit.
这是武当自家的真气炼法
(Treatise of the Most Exalted One) You have Dahuangting now.
有了大黄庭
It might help you.
可以参考一下
Goodbye then.
就此别过
Here is one thing.
跟你商量个事
Don't tear down the hut
那茅屋先别拆
and grow some vegetables for me
院子里
in the garden.
再帮我种点蔬菜
What kind of vegetables?
种什么
Just like before.
就跟之前一样
Do you want me to steal vegetables again?
你又让我去偷菜园
You're the next master.
你是下任掌门
It's not hard.
不难
You'd better leave now.
世子你还是赶紧走吧
What?
干吗
Do you know how to ride a horse?
你会骑马吗
I don't. So what?
不会怎么了
Nothing.
没怎么
Get down!
你下去
How do you go back to North Liang
我下去了
if I get down?
你怎么回北椋
I'll learn by myself.
我自己学呗
I've restored the hut and the garden for you.
那茅屋跟菜园子都给你恢复了
It has nothing to do with me.
跟我没关系
I have one more thing to ask you before I leave!
走之前再问你个事
Go ahead.
你说
When exactly are you going to Jiangnan?
你到底什么时候去江南
You don't even have the courage to see my sister?
见我姐一面都不敢了
When I become the best in the world,
等我成为天下第一
I will be able to go down the mountain.
就能下山
After I go down the mountain,
下山之后
I'll go to see her.
就去见她
The best in the world?
天下第一
How long will it take?
要等多久
It's gonna happen.
会有那一天的
Let's go back to North Liang.
回北椋
They've left.
人走了
They asked you to go to Jiangnan?
让你去江南
Master Chonglou.
师兄
I do like Xu Zhihu.
我是喜欢徐脂虎
But I also like Wudang.
可我也喜欢武当
I'm not going to leave here
我成不了天下第一
until I become the best in the world.
我是不会下山的
It must be hard for you.
苦了你了
It's not hard.
我不苦
I'm just worried
我只是担心
that you place all your hope on me,
您把希望都交在我身上
but what if I can't be the best in the world?
可如果我成不了天下第一呢
We haven't had a match for years.
咱俩可是多年没有一较远近了
Well.
怎么样
Why don't we do it today?
今日比试比试
I don't think it's a good idea.
不好吧
Are you scared?
不敢了
Let's do it then.
比就比
Okay.
好
Well, Master Chonglou.
怎么样
I'm more energetic than you, right?
师兄
I don't have Dahuangting anymore.
我可是没了大黄庭的人
That was a glorious defeat.
这叫虽败犹胜
What does that
可是这种事情
have anything to do with Dahuangting?
跟大黄庭有什么关系啊
Xixiang.
小师弟
Just feel free to be yourself.
安心地做你自己
Our master and I won't make a mistake.
我和师父的眼光是不会错的
You will be the best in the world.
你就是未来的天下第一
When you come down the mountain,
当你下山的时候
you must leave in a grand way
可得风光点
and make me
给你大师兄
look good!
长长脸面
Okay!
好
The best in the world!
天下第一
You're finally back, Your Highness.
世子终于回来了
Is this the mark of Dahuangting?
这便是大黄庭的印记吗
It looks good on you.
瞧着还挺适合世子的
Do you all know it?
都知道了
We got the message.
消息全都传回来了
Congratulations on being endowed with civil and martial virtues.
还得恭喜世子文武双全
You must be tired.
世子累了
Please get inside and have some rest.
先进去歇息吧
Why are you all waiting outside?
你们怎么都等在城外啊
Something happened in the mansion.
府里出了点事
Let's go inside first.
世子进去再说吧
Son.
儿子
You are finally back.
终于把你等回来了
Wang Chonglou
你说这王重楼啊
is decisive indeed.
还真是果断
He actually passed his Dahuangting to you.
还真把这大黄庭传给你了
Never mind.
也罢
You must be hungry now.
饿了吧儿子
Look what I got for you.
看爹给你准备什么了
There are more.
还有啊
I found this good stuff for you.
爹给你找到了这个好玩意儿
I don't want to eat.
不吃不吃不吃
What happened in the mansion?
这府里是出什么事了
What are you doing here?
你怎么跑这儿来了
Your Highness.
回世子
It's nothing serious.
其实没什么大事
Just to stay away from trouble.
就是避避风头
Stay away from trouble?
避风头
The Lord of North Liang came here to stay away from trouble?
北椋王跑到这儿来避风头
Is there a ghost in the mansion?
府里闹鬼了
it was a ghost.
闹鬼倒好了
Your second sister is back.
你二姐回来了
You told her that I'm learning martial arts?
你把我学武的事告诉她了
Do I need to tell her?
还用我告诉她吗
The whole world knows it now.
这天下人都知道了
I'd better go back to Wudang and stay there for a few days.
我还是回武当待几天吧
Wait, wait, you can't leave.
这这这不成 这
Listen.
我跟你说啊
I've told her
我已经告诉她
that you're on your way back to North Liang.
你在回北椋的路上了
She is waiting for you at home.
她现在正在家里等着你呢
Xu Xiao!
徐骁
You sold me out!
你这是把我顶前面了
I have to save
咱们父子俩
one of us.
总得保一个下来吧
It's not necessary.
这 何必呢
Do you see her?
你看见她了
She should be in my yard.
她应该在我院里
Go back to your rooms.
你们先回自己房间吧
I'll go to see her myself.
我一个人见她
Stay here!
待这儿
You're back to spend the New Year?
姐回来过年啊
(Artificers' Record) I made you a set of pieces with rocks
我在武当用山石
in Wudang.
给你刻了一副棋子
Take a look.
您瞧瞧
You must be tired of reading.
看书累了吧
Let me massage your shoulders.
我给你揉揉肩
Are you getting used to
姐在上阴学宫
the life at Shangyin Academy?
待得还习惯吗
I heard you are learning martial arts.
听说你学武啊
Old Huang died in Wudi City.
老黄死在了武帝城
I want to take his sword box back.
我想把他剑匣取回来
You think it's bad to learn martial arts?
姐觉得学武不好
- It's up to you. - Um.
学武随你啊
I just didn't expect
我只是没想到
that Old Huang is more important to you
在你眼里
than North Liang.
老黄胜过了北椋
Why do you say that?
这怎么说
Right now,
到了今天
you haven't even decided to take over the army of Xu.
你都还没有决定接过徐字旗
I don't think I'm up to
我是觉得自己无法胜任
such an important task.
这千斤重担
Enough!
够了
Weixiong.
姐
You can do
你想怎么做
whatever you want.
随你
Thank you for being so generous.
多谢姐高抬贵手
Where are you going?
姐你去哪儿
Don't be mad.
姐你消消气
I'll go back to Shangyin Academy right now.
我马上回上阴学宫
I won't be angry
看不到你
if I don't see you.
我就不生气了
You're going back now?
你这就回去
Not to spend the New Year at home?
年都不过了
I made it for you in person.
这我亲手给你刻的
Take a look, at least.
你好歹看一下
I've seen it.
我看过了
I'm not a kid anymore!
姐我不是小孩儿了
You all want me to take over North Liang!
你们都想让我接手北椋
Have you asked me if I want to?
没问我愿不愿意吗
Who are you to say no?
你有什么资格说你不愿意
Everyone should have the right to decide how to live his life!
每个人都应该决定自己的活法
You know nothing!
你什么都不明白
Your life is totally wasted!
白活了这么久
You can't even see your responsibility!
你连你自己身上的责任都看不到
Why are you here?
怎么是你
I heard that you tried to kill Xu Fengnian again.
听说你又刺杀过徐凤年
You're afraid to admit it?
不敢认
Yes.
是
I did try to kill him.
我是刺杀过他
Let me warn you.
我警告你
Don't forget who you are.
别忘记自己的身份
Well.
怎么
A maid can't assassinate the son of a lord?
丫鬟就不能刺杀世子了
I'll say it one last time.
我跟你说最后一次
If you hurt Xu Fengnian,
如果伤到徐凤年
I'll throw you into a well
我一定会把你扔到井里
and close it.
封了井盖
You'll just rot in the well
让你就这么烂在井里
and never see the sun again.
永世不能再见到天日
If you understand my words,
听懂的话
write it down
白纸黑字写下来
and swear
发誓你以后
that you will never try to kill Xu Fengnian again.
再也不会对徐凤年出手
Okay.
行啊
You want me to write it down?
写字是吧
Bring me a brush.
你给我支笔
The bigger, the better.
越大越好
Remember what I said.
记住我说的话
I, Xu Weixiong,
我徐渭熊
am a person
说到的
of my words.
自然会做到
What a coincidence,
巧了
so am I.
我也一样
Miss Weixiong rode away
二小姐策马而去
and left Lingzhou.
已经出了陵州
She came and left like the wind.
她倒是来去如风
It turns out
闹半天
she came all the way back
千里迢迢赶回来
just to scold me.
就是为了骂我两句
Miss Weixiong has high expectations for you.
二小姐对世子的期望很高
She is the first prodigy
她是上阴学宫
at Shangyin Academy for decades.
数十年来第一奇才
I'm no match for her,
我可比不了
and I don't want to learn it.
也不想学
Did Jiang Ni write it?
姜泥写的
Her handwriting is good.
这字不错
Chen Zhibao.
陈芝豹
You should have learnt a lot
你在上阴学宫
at Shangyin Academy.
应该学了诗书礼乐
Why do you care
我学什么
what I learnt?
与你何干
You've learnt so much,
学了这么多
but you are still so brutal.
杀气还这么重
I think Shangyin Academy is a good place for you.
我觉得上阴学宫很适合你
So?
所以呢
So, you don't need to come back to North Liang
所以如果没事的话
if there is nothing important.
你就别再回北椋了
Do you think I'm the cause of the chaos?
你觉得我是乱世之因
Father.
义父
Chen Zhibao left the camp alone
陈芝豹独自出营
and stopped Miss Weixiong outside the city.
将二小姐拦在城外
Father.
义父
Should we dispatch soldiers?
要不要调兵啊
They haven't seen each other for a long time.
久别重逢
Don't disturb them.
别打扰人家
Why do you want to see me?
找我干吗
Where is the mark of Dahuangting?
大黄庭怎么没了
There is no mark on Wang Chonglou
王重楼不发功的时候
when he doesn't use his force.
也看不出来
What is this?
做什么
It's Wudang's Treatise of the Most Exalted One.
武当的太玄感应篇
Hong Xixiang gave it to me.
洪洗象给的
It's for you.
给你的
I don't have Dahuangting.
我又没大黄庭
I'm too lazy to read.
我懒得读
Why don't you read it to me?
不如你念给我听
Don't even think about it.
想得美
I'll give you one penny
每读一字
for each word.
给你一文
One penny?
一文钱
One penny for each word.
一字一文
Two pennies.
两文
Just one penny.
就一文
If you read more books,
你多读几本
it can still cost me all of my money.
一样能读穷我
There is more than one book?
不止一本
Think about it.
你想啊
I want to learn martial arts,
我要习武
so, I have to read books.
就得读书
Let's just use this book as an example.
就说眼前这一本太玄感应篇
I asked Hongshu to roughly count it.
我让红薯粗略算了算
It's about 6,000 words.
大概六千来字
After you read the whole book,
全本读完
I'll pay you seven strings of pennies
我算你七贯钱
to make a good start.
开张酬宾
It's to your profit.
你很划算
Pay me every time after I finish one book.
一本一付
Okay.
行啊
There was something undefined and complete,
有物混成
coming into existence before Heaven and Earth.
先天地生
How still it was and formless,
惟象无形
abstruse and profound,
窈窈冥冥
standing alone.
寂寥淡漠
Too rigid.
太死板
Read it with emotions.
有感情些
There was something undefined and complete,
有物混成
coming into existence before Heaven and Earth.
先天地生
Be more sedate.
稳重些
What do you want?
你到底要怎么样
I pay you to read for me.
我花钱请你读书
Shouldn't you read it well?
你是不是应该有点质量
I'm going out now.
我出去一趟
Keep reading
你先读着
and think about
好好想想
the best way to read it.
怎么读最合适
I'll listen to it when I come back.
我再回来听
Your handwriting is good.
你那字写得不错
It's okay.
还行吧
My second sister snapped at you,
我二姐凶你
but you swore to kill me.
你发誓杀我
Is that appropriate?
合适吗
Xu Weixiong cares about you the most.
徐渭熊最疼的就是你
She wouldn't care if I swear to kill her.
说杀她
She cares about me?
疼我
She came all the way back
千里迢迢赶过来
just to scold me.
就为了骂我几句
That's because she is too disappointed in you.
那是对你失望透了
Why does she
你说我二姐
want me to take over North Liang so badly?
为什么一定要让我接手北椋啊
What question is that?
这不废话吗
My second sister hates
我二姐最痛恨的
the inheriting system the most.
就是世家门阀嫡子传承那一套
She wants me to take over North Liang
所以她让我接手北椋
certainly not for continuing the bloodline of the Xu family.
肯定不是为了徐家血脉
She must have other reasons.
她有别的原因
Then why don't you want to take over
那你不愿意接手北椋
North Liang?
到底是为什么
I don't want to see
我不想看到
people keep dying for this thing.
一直有人为了这件事而牺牲
But if you don't do anything,
那你什么都不做
doesn't it mean that they die for nothing?
那些人不就白牺牲了
Where are you going?
你去哪儿